创世之初 冥冥之中
In the beginning, there was darkness,
随着一声爆炸
and then, bang--
诞生了无尽膨胀的
giving birth to an endless expanding existence
时间 空间和物质
of time, space and matter.
每一天 新的发现都在揭秘这个诡异
Every day, new discoveries are unlocking the mysterious,
震撼 神秘莫测的
the mind-blowing, the deadly secrets
地方 - 我们所谓的《宇宙》
of a place we call "The Universe."
行星地球的毁灭
The destruction of planet Earth.
这个想法激发了无尽的预言 预测
The idea has inspired endless prophecies, predictions,
以及科幻故事
and science fiction stories.
人们可以胡思乱想种种刺激的场景
One could imagine all kinds of exciting scenarios.
瞬间汽化
Instant vaporization.
极度的拉面过程(spaghettification)
Extreme spaghettification.
反物质破坏
Antimatter devastation.
现在天王星和天文物理学领域的顶尖专家
Now leading experts in the fields of astronomy and astrophysics
想出各自的招术来摧毁地球
devise their own plots to destroy the Earth.
你会看到大楼熔化
You would have buildings melting.
物质一下子没了
Matter would turn into goo.
靠重力维系的一切分崩瓦解了
Everything that's held together by gravity would disintegrate.
这是一种爆炸式方式来揭示我们地球
It's an explosive way to uncover the extreme science
和宇宙的极端科学
of our planet and the universe.
请看地球终结的10个景象 -
Get set for 10 visions of terrestrial termination:
十大毁灭地球之招
"10 Ways to Destroy the Earth."
千万别随便尝试
Don't try this at home.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://www.hdcmct.com
影片压制:暮云春树  字幕来源：HDC字幕组 调校：晴天 招募Q号: 76846146
历史频道 - 宇宙 第4季第6集 十大毁灭地球之招
The History Channel - The Universe s04e06 10 Ways To Destroy The Earth
生存
Survival.
这是一场比赛 我们地球每天都在对抗着好斗的宇宙
It's a game our planet plays every day against an aggressive universe.
好球
Got it.
然而45亿年来 双方势均力敌
But for 4 1/2 billion years, the sides have been evenly matched,
所以比赛还在继续
so the game goes on.
场上的种种情况都能置我们于死地
There are all kinds of things out there that could kill us,
但是它们全都没得逞
but none of them have managed it.
有些威胁 如遥远星系发出的高能伽玛射线暴
Some threats, like hyper intense gamma ray bursts
与我们失之交臂
from distant galaxies, miss us completely.
其他危险从来就没通过我们无形的屏障
Other dangers never make it through our invisible barriers.
地球的磁场挡住了危险的带电粒子
Earth's magnetic field keeps out dangerous charged particles.
臭氧层过滤了紫外线辐射
The ozone layer filters ultraviolet radiation.
尽管宇宙都想不出
But even though the cosmos can't figure out
如何摧毁地球
how to destroy the Earth,
但是某些科学家却有自己的想法
some top scientists have their own ideas,
如布鲁斯 贝茨博士
like Dr. Bruce Betts,
地球面临小行星及其它太空碎片威胁方面的一位专家
an expert on the risks Earth faces from asteroids and other space debris.
摧毁地球最中意的方法 在我较为疯狂的念头里
A favorite way to destroy the Earth, in my more maniacal moments,
我或许会坚持到底
I'd probably go with my roots
把一个大小合适的物体撞入地球
and slam a nice-sized object into the Earth.
那么我们就来历数灾难 从第十招开始 -
And so our countdown to catastrophe commences with number 10:
招术之十 - 天地大冲撞
砰然撞在一起
Slammin' things together.
这是地球毁灭的集卡拉力赛
It's the monster truck rally of Earth destruction.
不过贝茨知道要粉碎地球谈何容易
But Betts knows that smashing the Earth isn't so easy.
可恶的撞击会造成破坏
Nasty impacts cause destruction,
但是它们并不擅长摧毁整个地球
but they're not very good at destroying the entire Earth,
尽管它们可以抹去大量的生命
even though they may wipe out significant amounts of life,
如6500万年前对待恐龙
like 65 million years ago with the dinosaurs
以及70%的地球物种
and 70% of the species on Earth.
问题何在？
The problem?
毁灭战士小行星可惜没有足够的个头
The dino-dooming asteroid just didn't have enough mass
来彻底毁灭地球
to completely destroy the planet.
小行星稍大于珠峰
The asteroid was a little bigger than Mount Everest,
听上去骇人 退避200英里就没事了
which sounds impressive until you step back about 200 miles.
如果我们站在全球的实际尺度上
If we had a globe that was actually to scale,
你就会感到喜马拉雅山
you wouldn't be able to feel the Himalayas
就是你的手指尖
with the tips of your fingers.
它们在我们看来很大
They look huge to us,
但是相对地球的实际尺度 就宛如蚁丘
but compared to the actual size of the Earth, they're like ant hills.
我们需要的东西至少是半个地球大 10分之一的质量
We need something at least half the size of the Earth and 1/10th as massive,
每秒30英里的速度奔向我们
heading for us at 30 miles a second.
来试试火星吧
Let's try Mars.
你可以改变火星的轨道 使其往里面来
You could change Mars' orbit, throw it inwards,
直到末日大冲撞
and lead to the doomsday impact.
随着它们彼此靠近
Even as they approach each other,
它们的重力会将它们拉在一起
their own gravities are going to pull each other together
最终死缠在一块
in a final death cling.
随着红色行星填满地球的天空
As the Red Planet fills Earth's skies,
巨大的海啸抹去了岛屿和沿海城市
enormous tsunamis obliterate islands and coastal cities.
于是情况变得糟糕极了
Then things get very bad.
如果你呆在地球的火星撞击的那一侧
If you live on the side of the planet where Mars hits,
就瞬间汽化了
instant vaporization.
没有被撞击的那一侧将会遭遇大地开裂的地震袭击
The side that doesn't get hit is struck by continent-cracking earthquakes.
撞击产生的热量将把所有的森林变成火海
The heat from the impact turns every forest into an inferno.
地球和火星熔化的山脉被抛入太空
Molten mountains of Earth and Mars, thrown into space,
雨点般落下 形成末日豪雨
rain back down in an apocalyptic shower of destruction.
撞击后一小时
An hour after impact,
地表上所有的生命死了个精光
whatever lived on the surface of the Earth is dead.
不过地球非常大 有60亿兆吨的岩石和金属
But Earth is so big, 6 billion trillion tons of rock and metal,
即使是火星的直接撞击会让星球遭遇重创
that even a direct hit from Mars would leave the planet itself damaged,
但基本完好无损
but essentially intact.
真正要摧毁地球就需要有更大的东西来打击我们
Really destroying the Earth requires something bigger hitting us,
如我们的姐妹行星 - 金星
like our sister planet, Venus.
你说到了类似的直径
You're talking a very similar diameter,
你说到了地球质量的80%以上
and you're talking over 80% of the mass of Earth.
因此如果金星袭击我们 撞击地球 我们就死定了
So if Venus comes at us and hits the Earth, we're toast.
两个星球将粉身碎骨
Both worlds shatter.
大量的碎片将飞入太空
Huge fragments shoot into space.
不过行星碎片也会落回
But planetary rubble will also fall back
并合并成为地球-金星混合体
and coalesce into an Earth-Venus amalgam,
大于两颗原先的行星的任何一个 如月球一般死寂
bigger than either original planet and as dead as the Moon.
绝对是摧毁地球的好方法
Definitely a good way to destroy the Earth.
但是其可能性有多大？
But how likely is it?
45亿年前 有大如火星的东西打击过我们
4 1/2 billion years ago, something as big as Mars did hit us.
在早期熔化的地球冷却过程中
The early molten Earth was still cooling
有一颗不大的行星猛烈撞上了我们
when a smaller planet struck us hard.
就像是球击打在沙地里 溅出一束颗粒
It's like a ball hitting in the sand, knocking a bunch of particles.
该物体炸掉了部分地球的地壳
The object blew off part of the Earth's crust
在地球周围形成了一个碎片盘
and formed a disk of debris around the Earth.
源自碎片 月球在随后不久就形成了
From that debris, the Moon formed quite shortly thereafter.
虽然行星撞击时有可能的
But while planetary impacts are possible,
但毕竟金星距离地球超过了2300万英里
Venus is more than 23 million miles from Earth,
火星则至少是在3500万英里外
and Mars is at least 35 million miles away.
所以你如何让它们从那里到这里？
So how would you get them from there to here?
行星通常处在非常稳定的轨道上
Planets are normally in very stable orbits.
但要是发生了把行星整个
But what if something happened
甩出其正常轨道的事情又当如何呢？
that threw a planet completely out of its normal orbit?
水星 最靠近太阳的行星
Mercury, the innermost planet to the Sun,
有着大椭圆轨道
has a rather elliptical orbit.
它常受到其他行星的各种重力干扰
It's subject to various gravitational perturbations by other planets.
而水星轨道的变化
Such changes in Mercury's orbit
也会间接影响到其他行星的轨道
can also indirectly affect the orbits of other planets,
尤其是 火星会占据一个轨道
and, in particular, Mars could take on a trajectory
有朝一日穿越地球的轨道
that could some day intersect the orbit of the Earth.
据说真实的火星撞地球的概率是
Some say the odds of a real-life Mars-Earth collision
40亿年的周期里1%的机会
are 1% over a period of 4 billion years,
完全无庸担心 但并非不可能
not likely enough to worry about, but not impossible.
想象一下 这整个体育场里有一只苍蝇
Imagine that there is a single fly in this entire stadium,
在球门之间飞来飞去
and it's flying from goalpost to goalpost.
如果我像这样用手去抓
If I just go like this with my hand,
我有机会逮住拿苍蝇吗？
what are the chances that I'm going to catch that fly?
你不会说机会等于零
You wouldn't say it's zero,
因为确实没有理由说为何不会发生
because there's no real reason why it can't happen,
但是你会说机会极小
but you would say it's extremely small.
行星撞击是毁灭地球的一个途径
Planetary impact is one way to destroy the Earth,
但是我们才开了个头
but we're just getting started.
现在你如果想要一个更长 更慢 更痛苦的过程
Now if you want to have a longer, slower, more painful process,
那么或许你会终结于地球轨道的因故改变
then perhaps you end up having the Earth's orbit modified somehow,
也就是终结于渐渐远离太阳
so that it ends up moving outwards from the Sun.
欢迎来到毁灭地球第9招
Welcome to the number 9 way to destroy the Earth:
招术第九 - 大冻结
在正常情况下 我们的椭圆轨道
Under normal circumstances, our elliptical orbit
让我们距离太阳 在1月份比7月份远上300万英里
takes us 3 million miles farther from the Sun in July than in January.
赤道以北在7月份温暖的原因
The reason it's warm in July north of the equator
在于那时北半球斜向了太阳
is because that's when the northern hemisphere tilts towards the Sun.
如果我们每年将地球拉远300万英里
If we spun the Earth away from the Sun at 3 million miles a year,
旅程不会立马致命
the journey wouldn't be instantly fatal.
我们移动一点点的话 我们是能够应付的
If we move a little bit, yeah, we can deal with it.
我们多穿点衣服就是了
We wear more jackets.
如果我们一路走远 那么事情就开始变得糟糕了
If we keep moving farther out, then things start to get uglier.
到了距离太阳2亿英里处
At almost 200 million miles from the Sun,
阳光就只有约三分之一了
the light is only about 1/3 as bright.
这将扼杀大部分农作物
This would kill off most crops.
整个食物链将遭破坏
The whole food chain would be broken down
如果地球距离太阳渐行渐远的话
if the Earth were to go zooming away from the Sun.
要是你真玩这个游戏
And if you really play this game,
要是你走出了海王星的轨道 那么
if you get out at the orbit of Neptune, say,
你就可能开始冻结住我们的大部分大气
you might start freezing out most of our atmosphere.
好天气就是零下350度
A nice day is 350 degrees below zero.
冰面上毫无生机
Nothing survives on the icy surface.
海洋是冰天冻地的坟墓
The oceans are frozen graveyards.
不过在冰面2 5英里以下 水还是液态的
But 2 1/2 miles below the surface, the water is still liquid,
幸亏来自海底火山的热量
thanks to the heat from undersea volcanoes.
这些热液喷口喷出的氢氧化硫
Sulfur hydroxide from these hydrothermal vents
会继续供养大管虫
will continue to feed large tube worms
以及其他怪异的化学合成生命形式
and other exotic forms of chemosynthetic life.
地核源源不断输出的热量
Continuing heat from the Earth's core
或许也能帮助人类生存在地下城市里
may also help humanity survive in cities below the surface.
人类是非常有弹性的物种
Mankind is a very resilient species,
如果地球不断盘旋到这个冰天冻地的死亡轨道上
and if the Earth were spiraling out on this freezing death orbit,
那么我想极有可能我们会找到钻入地下的办法
then I think it's very likely that we would find ways to dig in underground.
你可以利用地热能源将某些冻结的材料转换回
You could use the geothermal energy to convert some of the frozen materials back into
液态 将一些水转成你所需的氧和氢
the liquids and turn some of the water into oxygen and gases that you need.
地下农场或许能供养几百万人
Subterranean farms might support a few million people.
它可能并不漂亮
It might not be pretty,
但是地球及其至少部分子民得以生存下来
but the planet and at least a fraction of its people could survive.
但是那不是毁灭地球第八招的情形
But that's not the case with the number 8 way to destroy the Earth,
移向太阳 并
zooming toward the Sun and
招术第八 - 大燃烧
试想一下每年接近太阳300万英里的情景
Imagine getting 3 million miles closer to the Sun every year.
术语全球变暖甚至都来不及描述这种状况
The term global warming doesn't even begin to describe the situation.
是极地冰盖融化吗？
Liquefying polar ice caps?
那只是开头几年的事
That's just the first few years.
海平面或许会升高200英尺
The sea level may rise 200 feet,
然而所有的海水都将变成蒸汽
but all that water is about to turn to steam.
如果你移到金星所呆的地方 走近太阳三分之一的距离
If you move to where Venus is, a third of the way in towards the Sun,
你就到了那个点 开始失去液态水
you're going to get to the point where you start losing the liquid water,
开始变成蒸汽
and it's going to be going to vapor.
你最终得到了二氧化碳的大气层
You end up having a carbon dioxide atmosphere,
有严重的温室效应
and you have a massive greenhouse effect,
最终 地表温度之高
and you end up with a hotter surface
甚至都超过了你没有大气层的情景
than you even would if you had no atmosphere.
从阿拉斯加到澳大利亚
From Alaska to Australia,
平均温度达到了900华氏度
the average temperature is 900 degrees Fahrenheit.
复杂生命通通死光光
All complex life is dead,
地球自身义无反顾地最终跌入
and the planet itself is headed for a final plunge
太阳的核心
into the nuclear heart of the Sun.
天文学家和天体物理学家
Astronomers and astrophysicists
列出了十大毁灭地球之招
have come up with 10 ways to destroy the Earth.
位列大冲撞和缓慢冻结之后
And after being smashed and slowly frozen,
地球自寻死路 旋入太阳 -
the planet's on a death spiral into the Sun
摧毁地球第八招 -
in the number 8 way to destroy the Earth:
招术第八 - 大燃烧
死寂 荒凉 窒息 伴随着温室气体
Dead, barren, and choked with greenhouse gases,
地球现在距离曾经给它带来生机的星球
the Earth is now just a few million miles away
就几百万英里远
from the star that once gave it life.
最终 我们所留下的一切
Eventually, all that we would have left
或许就是一个熊熊燃烧的大球 一片焦土
would probably just be a big ball of burnt, charred cinder
正越来越靠近太阳
that's moving closer and closer to the Sun,
因为你太靠近太阳了
and as you got really close to the Sun,
甚至都已经蒸发殆尽了
even that would be vaporized away.
蒸汽将会被太阳风那样的影响吹走
The vapor's going to be moved away by effects like the solar wind.
你会看到它被剥离
You're going to strip it off.
我想 短时期内 看上去就像是彗星
And I suppose, for some brief period, it would look like a comet.
最后 就剩下核心
At last, only the core remains,
4300英里宽的铁 镍及放射性金属的球体
a 4,300-mile-wide ball of iron, nickel, and radioactive metals
温度如太阳表面 但比其小了200万倍
as hot as the Sun's surface, but 2 million times smaller.
最终其实会撞上太阳的
And that's what would end up actually colliding with the Sun.
太阳或许甚至都连喷嚏都不打一个
And the Sun probably wouldn't even hiccup or cough.
改变我们的轨道到如此致命的地步
To change our orbit so fatally
或许就在于一颗离家出走的太阳
would probably take nothing less than a runaway Sun
从N多光年以外过来
from many light-years away,
扰乱整个太阳系的重力
disrupting the gravity of the entire solar system.
恒星来串门的概率可谓
The chances that a star will come by sufficiently close and do that
微乎其微
are very, very small.
不过这并非天方夜谭 在未来的几百万年里
But it's not inconceivable that sometime in the next few billion years,
是会发生的
that will happen.
扰乱地球的绕日轨道意味着漫长的死亡过程
Disrupting the Earth's solar orbit means a long, drawn-out death.
然而停止地球的旋转将会是残暴的终结
But stopping its rotation would be a very violent end.
那就是毁灭地球第7招
That's the number 7 way to destroy the Earth:
招术第七 - 停摆
你一旦制动地球
If you stop the Earth,
但是物体并不会在地球上原地不动
but not the objects that are standing around on the Earth,
会继续往前的
those objects would keep on going.
比如 你会被高速抛到墙壁上
So for example, you would get thrown at a wall at a really high speed.
地球的运动速度为时速1000英里
The Earth is moving about 1,000 miles per hour.
如果你紧急刹车
And if you suddenly stopped,
大气不一定会随之停下
the atmosphere wouldn't necessarily stop with it.
因而 你立马就会有时速1000英里的大风
And so, instantly, you would have a 1,000-mile-an-hour wind
同时出现在地球的每个角落
everywhere on the planet at once.
与此同时 大量的内部旋转摩擦
At the exact same time, vast amounts of built-up rotational friction
会释放出巨大的热量
would be released as tremendous heat.
你会看到岩石熔化了 大楼熔化了
You would have rocks melting, you would have buildings melting.
很快 地球就变成了一个围绕太阳的阴曹地府
Soon the Earth would be a dead world orbiting the Sun.
我们的日夜周期将被年所替代
Our day-night cycle would be dictated by the year,
时间以地球绕日计算
the time it takes for the Earth to orbit the Sun.
白昼是半年长 夜晚是半年长
And a day would be half a year long and a night would be half a year long.
一面吸收太阳的热量是一次六个月
One side would absorb the Sun's heat for six months at a time,
此时黑暗面将失去热量
while the dark side would lose heat.
将出现两个季节 坏与更坏
There would be two seasons, bad and worse.
高温面和寒冷面之间的差异
This difference between the hot side and the cold side
会最终产生出巨大的疾风
is going to end up creating massive wind jets
从一侧流向另一侧 巨大的对流
streaming from one side to another, massive convection currents.
纵贯南北两极 日照面与黑暗面之间的阴影地带
From pole to pole, the shadow area between the light and dark sides
布满了巨大的气旋
would be filled with massive cyclones.
随着地球围绕太阳运动
As the Earth moves around the Sun,
两条1 2万英里的极端气候地带将扰动整个地球
the two 12,000-mile bands of extreme weather would churn across the globe.
这样 每六个月
So every six months,
地球上每个地方都会有风暴季节
every spot on the Earth will have a cyclone season.
基本上 天昏地暗一团糟
Basically, big old hangin' mess.
那是个难以对付的烂摊子
It's a mess that's hard to engineer in reality.
你可以想象一下要是有东西以适当的方式撞上地球
You might imagine it happening if something were to collide with the Earth
以此来平衡地球旋转的
in just the right way, in such a way that balances
倾角之类情况
the tendency of the Earth to rotate and so on.
那种碰撞具有巨大的能量
That collision would have so much energy
将地球停摆 这并不会造成我们的主要忧虑
that the stopping of the Earth wouldn't be our main concern.
地球停摆可能好可怕
As awful as stopping the Earth's rotation might be,
但它至少将我们的星球留下继续是太阳系的一个成员
it at least leaves our planet as a member of the solar system.
然而太空中的危险力量
But there are dangerous forces out in space
可以消除地球的每一个物理痕迹
that can remove every physical trace of Earth,
如塌缩星体的超致密残骸 即所谓的黑洞
like the ultra dense remnants of collapsed stars called black holes.
黑洞最危险的区域就是事件视界
A black hole's greatest area of danger is its event horizon:
有去无回的重力点
a gravitational point of no return.
物体一旦经过 就踏上了不归路
If something is crossing it, there is no way that it can go back out.
它吞噬周围奔向它的时空
It sucks the space-time around it towards itself,
因而出现在那个时空里的物质
so that matter just present in that space-time
也会被吸入黑洞
also gets sucked into the black hole.
典型的恒星级黑洞
A typical stellar-mass black hole
其质量约是太阳的5到10倍
weighs in at around 5 to 10 times the mass of the Sun.
把那样的东西放在地球旁边
Putting something like that next to the Earth
那肯定会摧毁地球的
would certainly destroy the planet.
不过我们来搞点好玩的
But let's make it more interesting.
要是地球处在两个黑洞之间呢？
What if the Earth were between two black holes?
有两个黑洞 乐趣就加倍了
With two black holes, you'd have double the fun.
那就是毁灭地球第六招
And that's the number 6 way to destroy the Earth:
招术第六 - 两个黑洞之间的蹂躏
其中一个黑洞会拽拉地球靠近它的一面
One of the black holes would pull on the near side of the Earth
甚于中心 把它往外拽
more than on the center, stretching it out.
它同样会拽拉中心甚于远端
It would also pull on the center more than on the far side,
也在把它往外拽
stretching it out as well.
另一个 对面的黑洞同样没闲着
The other, oppositely directed black hole would do the same thing.
黑洞猛拽地壳 抬起构造板块
The black holes wrench the Earth's crust, lifting tectonic plates,
扭曲着下面的半固态岩石圈
and distorting the semi-solid lithosphere below.
熔岩浆引发了末日火山大喷发
Molten magma triggers apocalyptic volcanic eruptions,
黑洞滞留了大部分火山灰烬
and the black holes keep most of the ash and dust
不回落到地球
from falling back to Earth.
海洋上 高潮迭起 永不落潮
In the oceans, huge tides rise and never fall.
随着地球的各个部分落入黑洞
As parts of the planet fall into the black holes,
物质和气体转成了致命的能量
matter and gases turn into deadly energy.
落入黑洞的东西会爆发出X射线
The stuff falling into the black hole will be bursting out x-rays,
那些X射线会淹没地球
and these x-rays would flood the planet
杀死众生没商量
and kill everybody pretty quickly.
此时 地球被绷到了崩溃的边缘
Meanwhile, Earth is being stretched to its breaking point.
它们在两头拽拉地球
They would be stretching the Earth in opposite directions,
就像是著名的五马分尸
and it would be like that famous business of tying horses to the four limbs of someone
将其撕碎
and tearing them apart.
被拉长的地球是永远连接两个黑洞呢
Will the stretched-out planet forever link the black holes,
还是断在一半呢？
or will it snap in half?
在毁灭地球十招的排名中
On the list of 10 ways to destroy the Earth,
第六号判给了地球一个极坏的模样
number 6 finds the planet in very bad shape:
两个黑洞之间的蹂躏
Touring between two black holes.
这是重力拔河比赛
It's a gravitational tug of war
地球作为绳子 可承受不了那样的拉力
with Earth as a rope that can't withstand the strain.
你会看到一个极端的拉面案例
You would have a case of extreme spaghettification.
地球被拽向不同的方向
Earth would be pulled in each direction,
在两个方向上被拉伸到这两个黑洞
stretched in two directions toward both black holes
最终被扯断
and eventually ripped apart.
然后断开部分会被撕碎
And then those pieces would get ripped apart.
And those pieces would get ripped apart.
在最后的地球面条
After the last spaghetti strands of Earth
被鲸吞进事件视界之后
are violently sucked into the event horizons,
这两个黑洞就成了曾经摆放过地球的
the two black holes will be bookends
空书架上的书裆了
on the empty shelf where Earth once stood.
令人宽慰的是挣扎在两个黑洞之间的概率
It's comforting to know that the odds of being stretched
微乎其微
between two black holes are slim to none.
然而物理学家 科幻小说作家特拉维斯 泰勒
But physicist and science fiction author Travis Taylor,
他写过几本有关真实和虚构的太空威胁的书籍
who's written several books on real and imaginary threats from outer space,
他有另一个关于破坏性黑洞的想法
has another idea involving destructive black holes.
如果我想摧毁地球
If I wanted to destroy the Earth,
我最中意的就是把一个黑洞困在地核里
my favorite is that we trap a black hole in the core
吞噬掉地球
and eat the Earth away.
这样我就会登上飞船躲得远远的
So I would like to be on a spaceship way away
看它自己塌缩
to watch it collapse on itself.
那就是毁灭地球第5招
And that's the number 5 way to destroy the Earth:
招术第五 - 从内部吞噬
星级黑洞干活利落
A stellar-mass black hole would do the job quickly,
但是也有其它有趣之处
but there are other intriguing possibilities.
我们还能想到什么？
So what else can we think of?
没准黑洞的大小如我的耳环
Well, maybe the black hole is the size of my earring.
那样大小的黑洞具有地球本身的质量
A black hole that size would have the same mass as the Earth itself.
让我们把这个迷你黑洞通过北极落下去
Let's take the miniature black hole and drop it through the North Pole.
假设速度与角度刚好
Assume the speed and angle are just right
能让它在地球中心旋转
to have it end up rotating in the center of the Earth.
马上 我们就会知道出大错了
Right away, we'd know something was very wrong.
假如你想方设法把一个地球质量的黑洞
if you have somehow managed to get an Earth-mass black hole
放到地球中心 那么在地球的表面
at the center of the Earth, then on the surface of the Earth,
我们会突然感觉到两倍的重力效果
we would suddenly feel twice the effect of gravity.
突然之间 球会下降快好多
All of a sudden, a ball would drop much faster.
我们都会举步艰难
All of us are going to start hunching down.
在所有生命无奈挣扎时
While all living things struggle helplessly,
迷你黑洞却在吞噬着物质
the miniature black hole is sucking in matter.
它吃得越多 离地球末日就越近
The more it eats, the closer Earth comes to doomsday.
随着物质被它吞入
And as it's pulling material in,
它上面的物质都将发生垮塌
all the material above it is going to be collapsing.
这样我们就会大规模的地震发生
So we will be having enormously massive earthquakes going on,
地壳会变动
shifts in the crust.
会出现新的火山
There'd be new volcanoes,
因为新的地方有岩浆冒出
because new places where the magma can pop out
看来是这个黑洞造成的
would appear due to this black hole.
因此可以想象到各种刺激的场景
So one can imagine all kinds of exciting scenarios.
经过数月的灾变
After months of increasing cataclysms,
终曲将不到一个小时
the finale will take less than an hour.
地球开始自我垮塌
The Earth will start to collapse on itself,
然后那部分也会被吞入黑洞
and then that part would be eaten by the black hole, too.
或许喜马拉雅山是地球上最后的幸存之地
Perhaps the Himalayas will be the last place on Earth to survive
最后也会落入事件视界消失殆尽
before they too fall through the event horizon to disappear forever.
要是你登上飞船冷眼观察
If you were up on a spaceship and watching it,
或许看上去就像是你拿着一个蛋壳
it would probably look like you took an eggshell
莫名其妙地从内向外破碎了
and somehow crushed it from the inside out.
假如你能用绳子将每个点拴到
If you could attach a string at every point
蛋壳的内部 突然把它拉住
to the inside of the eggshell and yank it all at once,
那么你就会看到它就一下子垮塌了
then you would see it just immediately collapse on itself.
留下的就只有黑洞
All that would remain is the black hole.
地球的质量现在就存在于黑洞的内部
The mass of the Earth would just exist now inside that black hole.
还没人发现过地球级的黑洞
No one has ever found an Earth-mass black hole.
一般的黑洞只诞生于超新星
Normal black holes only form from the supernova death of stars
其质量至少比太阳大10倍
that were at least 10 times more massive than the Sun.
不过小100万倍的黑洞
But black holes with a million times less mass
有可能出现在宇宙间
might be out in the universe.
根据一种假设 大爆炸后不久
According to one hypothesis, shortly after the Big Bang,
许多物质打包在一起非常致密
there was so much matter packed so densely together
有数以百万计的迷你黑洞 所谓的原始黑洞
that millions of miniature, so-called primordial black holes
可能会形成 无需垂死的恒星
could have been formed without the need of dying stars.
我们不知道有这样的黑洞存在
We don't know of the existence of such black holes,
但是它们可能存在 可能会吃掉地球
but they could exist, and they could devour the Earth.
或许我们不想去找找试试看
Probably we don't want to go and find one of these just to try it out.
但是我们可不可以就在地球上创造一个迷你黑洞
But could we create a mini black hole right here on Earth,
或许就用粒子加速器
perhaps with a particle accelerator
比如欧洲的大型强子对撞机？
like the Large Hadron Collider in Europe?
那就是犹他州盐湖城的贾斯汀
That's what Justin L. from Salt Lake City, Utah,
向宇宙节目提出的问题
wanted to ask "The Universe."
他发短信给我们 -
So, he texted us
超级对撞机会产生黑洞吗？
Can a super collider cause a black hole?
贾斯汀 问得好
Justin, great question.
好多物理学家都想知道大型强子对撞机
A lot of physicists would like to know whether the Large Hadron Collider
是否会产生出迷你黑洞
will produce mini black holes.
原则上 可以
In principle, it can.
如果它将大量的材料压缩成充分小的体积
If it compresses a lot of material into a sufficiently small volume,
那么就会产生出一个黑洞
then it'll produce a black hole.
但是不用担心
But don't worry.
这种黑洞很快就会蒸发
Such black holes will quickly evaporate,
不会吃掉地球
and they won't devour the Earth.
太空中 黑洞的破坏力
In space, the destructive power of black holes
来自它们不可抗拒的重力 但是重力的匮乏
comes from their irresistible gravity, but a lack of gravity
可能会对地球造成更大的伤害
could be even more dangerous for the Earth.
那激起了天文学家亚历 菲利潘科的好奇心
That's what intrigues astronomer Alex Filippenko,
他开创性地研究暗能量
whose groundbreaking studies of dark energy
宇宙的加速激发了他自己的世界末日景象
and the acceleration of the universe have inspired his own vision of doom.
或许我最中意的毁灭地球的招术
Perhaps my favorite way to destroy the Earth
就是通过瓦解我们所谓的重力
is through a disruption of what we call gravity.
那就是摧毁地球第4招
And that's the number 4 way to destroy the Earth:
招术第四 - 关闭重力
我们所做的一切都取决于与重力的平衡关系
Everything we do depends on a balanced relationship with gravity.
但要是重力决定结束这种关系呢？
But what if gravity decided to end the relationship?
没有了重力 上去后就永远下不来了
Without gravity, what goes up will never come down.
飞机就永远不着陆了
Airplanes will never land.
树木扎根地面 直到地面破碎为止
Trees are rooted to the ground until the ground comes apart.
这一切只是真正的灾难到来的热身
And all that is just a warm-up for the real disaster to come.
地球本身会开始支离破碎
Earth itself would begin to break apart, piece by piece.
这貌似不可能 但重力真的会关闭吗？
It seems impossible, but could gravity really be switched off?
匪夷所思 答案是
Incredibly, the answer is
有可能
possibly.
在将来 重力可能不复存在
In the future, gravity may cease to exist.
在天文学家和天体物理学家炮制的
Of the 10 ways to destroy the Earth
十大地球毁灭之招中
cooked up by astronomers and astrophysicists,
最令人匪夷所思的一招就是第4招
one of the most incredible is number 4:
关闭重力
Turn off the gravity.
如今 重力是四种基本力之一 其它还有电磁力
Today, gravity is one of four basic forces, along with electromagnetism,
把原子核结合起来的强作用力
the strong nuclear force that holds atomic nuclei together,
放射线的源头 - 弱作用力
and the weak nuclear force that's the source of radioactivity.
然而在大爆炸的时候
But at the time of the Big Bang,
没有这四种基本力 可能只有两种力
instead of four fundamental forces, there may have only been two.
当宇宙成长到若干分之一秒时
When the universe was a tiny fraction of a second old,
强核力被统一在了所谓的弱电作用力里
the strong nuclear force was unified with what's called the electroweak force,
那是电磁力与弱作用力的混合体
an amalgam of electromagnetism and the weak nuclear force.
那种超级力的联合体或许创造了一个超级能量
That united super-force may have created a super-energy
可能导致了
that could have caused
宇宙的瞬间扩张 被称为是膨胀
an almost instantaneous expansion of the universe called inflation.
它在极端的时间内变得大得惊人
It became monstrously big in a very short amount of time.
然而在大爆炸后的瞬间时间里
But in a minuscule fraction of a second after the Big Bang,
膨胀停止 力分解了
inflation stopped as the forces broke up.
强作用力从弱电作用力里分裂出来
The strong nuclear force split apart from the electroweak force,
形成了原先统一力的两种不同的表现形式
becoming two different manifestations of this previously unified force.
如果一个看似统一的力可以一分为二
If a seemingly unified force could split in two,
那么它可不可以再次发生在重力身上呢？
can it happen again with gravity?
这种可怕的可能性可以用一枚简单的硬币来表述
This terrifying possibility can be represented with a simple coin.
硬币有两个面
A quarter has two faces,
但是你传递能量给硬币使其转起来
but if you impart energy to the coin by spinning it,
两个面似乎合并在了一起
the two faces seem to merge.
你显然看不清正反面
You see neither heads nor tails distinctly.
现在 最后 硬币失去了能量
Now, eventually, that quarter loses energy,
它落下时要么是正面要么是反面
and it lands either heads or tails,
两种截然不同的结果 任何一个看上去都不会是
two distinct outcomes, neither of which look like
球形对称的旋转的硬币
the spherically symmetric spinning quarter.
同样 现在对称的重力
In the same way, the symmetric gravity right now
也会有朝一日被分裂成两个不同的方面
could someday split into two different aspects.
两种新力中的每一个某种程度上都会表现得
Each of these two new forces would behave in a way
与目前的重力表现截然不同
distinct from the current behavior of gravity.
靠重力结合起来的一切都将瓦解
Everything that's held together by gravity would disintegrate,
会给地球上的我们招来厄运
and that would spell doom for us on Earth.
人的身体会保持不变
Human bodies would remain intact,
因为他们是靠电磁力 不是重力结合起来的
because they're held together by electromagnetic forces, not gravity.
但是地球上的每一个人都会飞起来 在太空中窒息而死
But everybody on Earth would fly up to suffocate in space,
此时地球自身开始解体
while the Earth itself would come unbound,
不再靠重力来结合了
no longer held together by gravity.
木星及其他气体巨星将会消失
Jupiter and the other gas giants would dissipate.
太阳 其重力曾经如拴在绳子上的球那样旋转行星
The Sun, whose gravity once spun the planets like balls on strings,
也会四分五裂
would fly to pieces.
太阳的大部分是巨大炙热的气体球
Most of the Sun is all a big, hot ball of gas anyway,
它的保持全靠它自身的重力
and it's held there by its own gravity.
所以你所看到的可能是星球弥散得飞快
So what you'd probably see is a star drift away rather quickly.
太阳不会结合起来了
The Sun wouldn't be held together.
星系不会结合起来了
The galaxy wouldn't be held together.
一切通通散开了
Everything would be drifting apart.
地球会变成宇宙一个角落里的
The Earth would be just random particles
宇宙尘埃的随机粒子
in a small corner of a universe of cosmic dust.
那将是个骇人听闻的结局
That would be a pretty amazing ending.
当然啦 还有另外一招把地球拆散
Of course, there is another way to take the Earth apart:
爆炸
blow it up.
容易吗？ 当然不
Easy? Of course not.
但是有一个方法
But there is a way.
创造某种反物质毁灭性炸弹
Create an antimatter devastation bomb of some sort.
那就是毁灭地球第3招
That's the number 3 way to destroy the Earth:
招术第三 - 反物质湮灭
这是天体物理学家克利福德 约翰逊的首选
And it's the first choice of astrophysicist Clifford Johnson.
反物质的想法只是其具有某种美
The antimatter idea just has a certain beauty to it.
从内而外的巨大的爆炸就是一种纯粹 可怕之美
It's just the sheer, terrible beauty of a really dramatic explosion from the inside.
反物质就像物质 只是相互对立
Antimatter is just like matter, only the opposite.
物质与反物质彼此湮灭在绚丽的烈焰之中
And matter and antimatter destroy each other in a blaze of glory.
基本上 这是爱因斯坦的E=mc平方在起作用
So, basically, this is Einstein's E=mc squared in action.
你可以把这个物质和反物质
You can take this matter and antimatter
合并在一起 释放出纯粹的能量
and combine it together and release pure energy.
一磅反物质湮灭一磅物质
Just one pound of antimatter annihilating one pound of matter
就具有44兆吨的爆炸当量
would pack 44 megatons of explosive punch,
相当于一颗氢弹
as much force as a thermonuclear bomb.
不过摧毁地球要更多的量
But destroying the Earth would take a lot more.
据估算
According to some estimates,
你至少需要100万亿吨的反物质
you'd need at least 100 trillion tons of antimatter.
想想这个体育场的规模
So thinking of the size of the stadium,
我们必须要有数以百万计的体育场来填满反物质
we would have to fill millions of stadiums with antimatter
才能够让它与地球上的物质进行互动
before it could interact with the matter on Earth
释放出足够的能量来将其拆散
to actually release enough energy to unbind it.
不过要是你真的想试试
But if you really want to try,
有座反物质工厂就在9300万英里外
there's an antimatter factory just 93 million miles away.
当足够的磁能堆积在太阳的核熔炉里时
When enough magnetic energy builds up in the nuclear furnace of the Sun,
就会释放出来形成太阳耀斑爆发
it's released in an explosive solar flare.
一个大耀斑可以生成
A big flare can generate
多达两磅的反物质
as much as two pounds of antimatter.
接触到物质几乎立马就毁灭了反物质
Contact with matter destroys the antimatter almost instantaneously,
但是有办法来收纳它
but there are ways of containing it.
你可以不用接触将其悬浮起来
You can suspend it without touching it
利用各种电磁场
by using various kinds of electric and magnetic fields.
你可以无限期地悬浮一些反物质
So you can keep a quantity of antimatter suspended indefinitely.
这样你所要做的一切就是从10万兆个
So all you have to do is collect and store antimatter
太阳耀斑里收集和储存反物质
from around 100 quadrillion solar flares.
一旦你有了100万兆吨的反物质
Once you've got your 100 trillion tons of antimatter,
就将其运到地球 关闭电磁场
just transport it to Earth and turn off the electromagnetic field
这样它就可以与普通物质相接触了
so it can come in contact with normal matter.
或许要将它放在地球中心 然后就听其摆布了
Maybe put it at the center of the Earth somehow and then let it do its thing.
它会向外爆炸 炸飞一切
It'll explode outward and simply rip everything apart.
虽然反物质爆炸是一瞬间的事
But while an antimatter explosion would be instantaneous,
但是收集所有的反物质却要化上上千亿年的时间
collecting all that antimatter would take tens of billions of years.
我们每年只有那么多的太阳耀斑
We only have so many solar flares a year.
需要N多 N多年的时间
It would take many, many, many years
来捕获和储存足够的反物质
to capture and store enough antimatter
来真正打造出规模极可观的炸弹
to really create a very appreciable-sized bomb.
物理学家知道反物质并非唯一的粒子
Physicists know that antimatter isn't the only type of particle
可以用来消灭地球
that could liquidate the planet.
毁灭地球第2招
The number 2 way to destroy the Earth
就是通过转换来摧毁的案例
is a case of destruction through transformation:
招术第二 - 通过奇异物质来转换
这是大麻烦始于小级别
This is big trouble that starts at a tiny level,
比质子和中子还小 是在怪异的夸克世界里
smaller than protons and neutrons, in the weird world of quarks.
粒子的名称有上夸克 下夸克 奇夸克
Particles with names like up, down, and strange.
尽量不要牵涉到太多的夸克术语
Try not to get hung up too much on the semantics of what a quark is.
你可能会说那是亚-亚原子级粒子
You might want to say it's a sub-subatomic particle,
就是构成其他东西的东西
the thing that makes up the other things.
有些物理学家认为等量的
Some physicists theorize that an equal number
上夸克 下夸克 奇夸克会构成奇异夸克团 -
of up, down, and strange quarks would make up a strangelet--
一种叫做奇异物质的粒子
a particle of something called strange matter.
它的奇异之处就在于它可以
What makes it so strange is that it might change
改变它所接触的任何东西的物理属性
the physical nature of whatever it touches,
就像冰块会冷却周围的水一样 只是更加极端罢了
like ice, cooling the water around it, only far more extreme.
它们喜欢将别的东西变成怪东西
They like to turn other things into strange things.
它们喜欢将一切都变得怪怪的
They like it all to be strange.
设想地球上的一切以及地球本身
Imagine everything on Earth and the Earth itself
都变成无机浆糊 全是因为亚原子奇异夸克团
turning to inorganic mush, all because of a subatomic strangelet.
幸运的是 地球上并无任何奇异夸克团
Fortunately, there aren't any strangelets on Earth.
然而在塌缩的太阳即中子星的内部
But inside the collapsed Suns called neutron stars,
有可能因为巨大的重力
it might be possible for the immense gravity
将上夸克 下夸克 奇夸克压缩在一起
to press together up, down, and strange quarks
形成奇异物质
into strange matter.
我们已非常接近答案了
We are getting very close to the answer.
我们有可能在未来几年里知道答案了
We might know in the next few years.
因此如果你在中子星里发现有微型奇异物质团的话
So if you did find a microscopic lump of strange matter in a neutron star,
设法将其带回地球 扔下去
somehow got it back to Earth, and dropped it,
比如 扔在帝国大厦的楼顶
say, on the top of the Empire State Building,
会发生什么情况？
what would happen?
A - 没事
"A,"nothing,
或 B
or "B"
所有这些奇异夸克
All these strange quarks
可能会改变地球上的物质形态
could change the state of matter here on Earth.
连锁反应启动了
A chain reaction has begun.
奇异物质团与普通物质发生了反应
The strangelets are reacting with ordinary matter.
地球在变化
The Earth is changing.
但是会变成啥模样？
But into what?
在十大摧毁地球之招的名录上
On the list of 10 ways to destroy the Earth,
招术2或许是最怪异的
number 2 is perhaps the strangest of all.
如果你想把整个星球转变成
If you wanted to convert the entire planet
一个大奇异夸克团的话
into a big bunch of strange quarks,
你要做的一切就是将奇异夸克到处放上一点
all you would need to do is put a few strange quarks here and there.
这样地球就会开始自己变得怪异
Then the Earth would start turning itself strange,
甚至有过之而无不及
even more strange than it is.
怪异物质
Strange matter,
被称为是奇异物质团的夸克物质团
a lump of quark material called strangelets,
把地球搞得松散 惊人的事件就发生了
has been let loose on Earth, and an astonishing event happens.
它接触的第一样东西变成了怪异物质
The first thing it touches turns to strange matter,
然后是第二样东西
then the next thing.
很快你就变成了怪异版的你
Pretty soon you would be a strange version of yourself.
即使我们在亚原子层面上观察
Even when we look at subatomic levels,
就是原子核层面上 还是有非常清晰的结构
just at the nucleus, there is a well-defined structure.
我们能够分辨出质子和中子 等等
We can tell apart protons and neutrons, et cetera,
但要是你失去了那种结构
but if you lost that structure,
物质就会失去我们熟悉的形状
then matter would lose the shape that we know of.
构成了单个元素的独特的轨道和粒子数量
The unique orbits and numbers of particles that make up the individual elements
现在形成了千篇一律的物质
now form an undifferentiated mass.
一切都变成了一模一样的怪异物质
Everything becomes the same strange matter,
从原子核到名胜古迹 到山脉
from atomic nuclei to monuments and mountains,
不管是死是活
and whatever is alive dies.
一旦启动 这种转变将是一发不可收拾
And once it starts, this transition would be fairly rapid.
它会将东西溶解成一个巨大的物质团
It would be like dissolving something into one huge glob of matter.
它会变成这种黏糊糊的夸克汤
It would turn into just this goo, this soup of quarks.
你最终会将整个地球转化成
You could end up converting the entire Earth
一大块怪异物质
into one big piece of strange matter.
原始黑洞
Primordial black holes,
重力的消失
the end of gravity,
反物质以及怪异物质
antimatter and strange matter.
理论物理学是否还有
Does theoretical physics
毁灭地球更为离奇的招术了呢？
have an even more bizarre way to destroy the Earth?
有
Yes.
事实上 天体物理学家菲耶尔 奥泽尔
In fact, astrophysicist Feryal Ozel
准备抹去地球
is ready to obliterate the Earth
连同现实的整个结构
along with the entire fabric of reality.
我想我最中意的炸毁地球之招
I think my favorite way of blowing up the Earth
就必须要有宇宙的某种巨大的相位转变
would have to be some kind of huge phase transition in the universe.
那就会把我们带到另一种形态
This would just take us into another state.
这就是毁灭地球第1招
It's the number 1 way to destroy the Earth:
招术之一 - 平行世界碰撞
它始于另一个科幻主题
It starts with another science fiction staple
许多物理学家现在当真了
that many physicists now take seriously,
存在着其它宇宙
the existence of other universes.
没准其他宇宙中存在着地球
It's possible that there are Earths in other universes.
把我们的宇宙想象为
Think of our universe
二维的薄片 存在于这里
as a two-dimensional sheet, which exists here,
活动在薄片里
and moving around in the sheet
就像是活动在我们的三维空间里一样
is like moving around in our three spatial dimensions.
然而你可以朝这另一个方向移动
But then you can move in this other direction,
这就要出薄片了
which is sort of off the sheet,
那里有另一个薄片
and there's another sheet there,
那将是个不同的宇宙
and that would be a different universe.
我们的宇宙或许就像那个
Our universe would be just like that one perhaps,
或许少有不同
or maybe slightly different,
但是极其重要的要意识到 我们不能让
but it's very important to realize that we shouldn't have
这两者碰撞在一起
these two things collide into each other.
设想我们的宇宙是一张纸 如这个
Imagine that our universe is a piece of paper, like this.
然后附近的宇宙将会是这张纸
Then a nearby universe would be this piece of paper.
现在假如这两张纸碰撞
Now if the two pieces of paper were to collide,
你可以听到那能量
you can hear that energy.
现在来想象两张宇宙般大小的纸相碰撞
Now imagine two sheets of paper the size of the universe colliding.
会有多少能量在那样的碰撞中泄漏出来？
How much energy would be imparted at a collision like that?
要是我们不知怎么的接触到了一个平行宇宙
If we somehow did make contact with a parallel universe,
那将会是我们所知的最后的事情了
it could be the last thing we'd ever know.
那将不仅是毁灭行星
It would not just destroy planets,
还会毁灭太阳系 星系 星系团
it would destroy solar systems, galaxies, clusters of galaxies.
将会毁灭一切
It would destroy everything.
将会是这个现存宇宙的终结
It would be the end of this current universe.
但是万物的终结会不会
But is it possible that the end of everything
是其它万物的开端呢？
is the beginning of everything else?
如果一个大爆炸创造了我们的宇宙
If one Big Bang created our universe,
那么另一个大爆炸会重新开始整个事情
then another Big Bang could start the whole thing over again.
它有可能创造另一个宇宙
It might create another universe.
或许这最不可思议的末日情景
And maybe this most incredible of doomsday scenarios
是唯一一个已经发生过的
is the only one that's already happened.
大爆炸说不定来自这样一对宇宙的碰撞
The Big Bang came from the collision of such a pair of universes perhaps.
因此没准会再次发生
So maybe it's going to happen again.
假如是这样
And if it does,
在经过100亿年
then after about 10 billion years
或许在另一个宇宙间存在着另一个地球
Maybe there would be another Earth in another universe.
我们看到了地球毁灭于突然撞击
We've seen the Earth destroyed by sudden impact,
严寒 酷热
bitter cold, and vaporizing heat.
它停止了自旋
It's been stopped in its rotation,
被怪异物质转换
transformed by strange matter,
被黑洞拉面和吞噬
spaghettified and swallowed by black holes,
破碎和炸毁 -
disintegrated and blown up--
至少是理论上的
at least in theory.
事实上 概率将是地球将继续旋转数十亿年
In reality, the odds are that the world will keep spinning for billions of years.
但是宇宙中有太多的事情
But there is so much in the universe
我们既无法知道也无法预测
we can neither know nor predict.
全新的地球在全新的宇宙中
A whole new Earth in a whole new universe.
那可能是截然不同的地方
That could be a totally different place,
甚至物理定律也完全迥异
even with different physical laws.
那意味着我们会有新的十大毁灭之招
That means we got think of ten new ways to destory the Earth.